Finding aid to Cambridge School of Architecture and Landscape Architecture records CA.MS.00078
Smith College Archives
Cambridge School of Architecture and Landscape Architecture records
1916-1998
Smith College Archives
Cambridge School of Architecture and Landscape Architecture
CA.MS.00078
1.667 linear feet (6 containers)
Educational institution developed in association with Harvard University, and later affiliated with Smith College, as a Graduate School of Architecture and Landscape Architecture. Contains Alumnae Bulletins, sketches, bookplates, certificates, brochures, correspondence, examinations, photographs, reports, slides, and information on student careers.
Biographical / Historical
The School was founded in 1915 as the Cambridge School of Architecture and Landscape Architecture, and was the first to produce women graduate training in these two professions, coordinated under a single faculty. Due to Harvard University's policy of a male institution, the school ran as a "little experiment" in the office of Henry Frost, professor of architectural design at Harvard University, with only nine to twelve students, all women. In 1924 it was incorporated under Massachusetts law as an educational institution. In 1934 the School was affiliated with Smith College as a Graduate School, retaining its own name and independent organization, but with the privilege of recommending its students to the College for the graduate degrees of Master in Architecture and Master in Landscape Architecture. Two years later the graduate degrees of Bachelor of Architecture and Bachelor of Landscape Architecture were introduced, preceding the Master's degrees, which since that time have been granted for advanced work. In 1938 the School became actually a part of Smith College as its Graduate School in the two professions for which it prepares students, while the school itself was to remain in Cambridge.
Scope and Contents
The Cambridge School of Architecture and Landscape Architecture Records are comprised of Alumnae Bulletins, sketches, bookplates, certificates, brochures, correspondence, examinations, photographs, reports, slides and information on student careers.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into four series:
I. Background
II. Alumnae
III. Correspondence
IV. Publications
Related Material
Smith College President's Office Records re: Cambridge School, 1927-1943
Dorothy May Anderson Papers, American Society of Landscape, 1976
Architects, Committee for Women in Landscape Architecture, Cambridge School Project, questionnaires to Cambridge School graduates
Records of the Smith College Committee on Graduate Instruction, 1933-1942
Conditions Governing Access
The papers are open for research according to the regulations of the Smith College Archives with the exception of student files which are restricted and closed to research use.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Cambridge School of Architecture and Landscape Architecture Records were donated by Dorothy May Anderson to the Smith College Archives.
Architecture--Study and teaching (Higher)--Massachusetts --Cambridge.; Landscape architecture--Study and teaching (Higher --Massachusetts--Cambridge.; Cambridge School of Architecture and Landscape Architecture; Smith College--History--Sources.
- SERIES I. BACKGROUND
  Scope and Contents
  Background contains information of examinations, exhibitions, faculty salaries, history of the school, photographs, reports and slides and books given to Smith College.
  - Examinations, 1938-1942 (Box 1298, Folder 1)
  - Exhibitions, 1929-1940; 1984 (Box 1298, Folder 2)
  - Faculty salaries, 1941-42 (Box 1298, Folder 3)
  - History of School, 1928-1973 (Box 1298, Folder 4)
  - Organization of school, 1924-1945 (Box 1298, Folder 5)
  - Photographs, 1935-1978; undated (Box 1298, Folder 6)
  - Report on the plan for Smith College, 1942 (Box 1298, Folder 7)
  - Report to the President of Smith College, 1938-1941 (Box 1298, Folder 8)
  - List: slides and books given to Smith College, 1942-46 (Box 1298, Folder 9)
- SERIES II. ALUMNAE
  Alumnae contains information on the work of former students.
  - General, 1919-1941 (Box 1298, Folder 10)
  - Baily, Jane Luce, 1921 (Box 1298, Folder 11)
  - Christiansen, Abby, 1977-79; undated (Box 1298, Folder 12)
  - Cunningham, Mary Parsons, 1973-1980 (Box 1298, Folder 13)
  - Greely, Rose Ishbel, 1998 (Box 1298, Folder 14)
  - Jones, Elizabeth Dickerman, undated (Box 1298, Folder 15)
  - Kirkwood, Grace Hight, 1986 (Box 1298, Folder 16)
  - McPhearson, Bertha Mather, 1993 (Box 1298, Folder 17)
  - Norcross, Katherine Brooks, 1976-1978 (Box 1298, Folder 18)
  - Power, Ethel B., undated (Box 1298, Folder 19)
  - Whitmore, Frances, 1933 (Box 1298, Folder 20)
  - Williams, Beatrice, 1982 (Box 1298, Folder 21)
  - Board of Trustees (Cambridge School): minutes, 1924-1945 (Box 1298, Folder 22-23)
  - Miscellaneous, 1935-1986 (Box 1298, Folder 24)
- SERIES III. CORRESPONDENCE
  Correspondence is comprised of general and course-related correspondence.
  - General
    - Nicolson, Marjorie H., 1933-1940 (Box 1299, Folder 1)
    - Ford, Harriet Bliss (trustee), 1935 (Box 1299, Folder 2)
    - President Neilson, 1926-1938 (Box 1299, Folder 3-4)
    - Presidents Neilson/Morrow/Davis, 1939-1940 (Box 1299, Folder 5)
    - President Davis, 1941-42 (Box 1299, Folder 6-7)
    - From alumnae, 1942 (Box 1299, Folder 8)
      General
      [See also File of correspondence-Trustees, Eleanor Raymond]
    - From trustees, 1942 (Box 1299, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence re: courses
    - Koch, Kate Ries, 1927-1940 (Box 1299, Folder 10)
      - booklet: course info, 1920-21 (Box 1299)
    - Larkin, Oliver W., 1936-1940 (Box 1299, Folder 11)
    - Putnam, Karl L., 1934-1941 (Box 1299, Folder 12)
    - Van Der Poel, Priscilla (Paine), 1940 (Box 1299, Folder 13)
- SERIES IV. PUBLICATIONS
  Publications consists of Alumnae Bulletins, architectural sketches by alumnae, bookplates, certificates, Alumnae Bulletin publications and school bulletins.
  - Alumnae Bulletins, 1928-1937 (Box 1300)
  - Small, untitled architectural sketch, undated (Box 1300)
  - Alumnae Bulletins, 1938 (Box 1301)
  - Bookplates, undated (Box 1301, Folder 1)
  - Certificates, 1940; undated (Box 1301, Folder 2)
  - Brochures, 1932-39; undated (Box 1301, Folder 3)
    [See also Slides]
  - Alumnae Bulletin publications, 1939-1942; 1978 (Box 1301, Folder 4)
  - School bulletins, 1916-1941 (Box 1301, Folder 5-6)
  - Student transcripts, 1920-1946 (Box 5)
    [These records are restricted and closed to research use. Please see the reference archivist for more information.]
  - Student files, 1916-1946 (Box 6)